another piece of information that the
cache maintains about each of the blocks
it has is the so-called valid bit if we
look at the cache with four blocks of
data and the tag that tells us which
block we have in each of the lines the
question is what happens when we turn on
the processor at that time the cache
contains no useful data but the data
will have some bits here even if all of
the bits are 0 we need to know that
whatever address we produce it doesn't
match any of these blocks here so that
we need to access memory and bring
actual data into the cache we do this by
matching the tag but what does the tag
initially have if the tag initially just
has all zeros what if we are accessing
address like this or it might happen
that this address actually has a tag
bits that correspond to 0 in that case
the initial tag would match this and we
would be accessing this garbage data in
the cache which hasn't been brought from
memory so we are really accessing
something that is not equal to what we
should be accessing note that any
possible value for the tag might match
the tag of an actual address so it is
not that it is wrong to initialize to 0
it's that any particular initial value
here would produce the same problem so
what we do is we add an additional bit
of state to the cache for each line that
tells us whether the tag and the data
are valid initially the valid bits need
to be set to 0 which means that if our
tag matches the address but the valid
bit is 0 we treat that as not a hit so
the hit condition is really the tag
matches our block number and the valid
bit is set to 1 by setting the valid
bits to 0 initially we make sure that
none of these can hit until real data is
brought in and thus we also remove the
problem of initializing the data and
attack we can leave anything here so
these don't need to be
zero doubt as long as the valid bit is
set to zero correctly so when we boot up
the processor we set all the valid bits
to zero and then when we bring stuff
from memory put the data here set the
tag to correspond to the blocks number
and at that time we also set the valid
bit to one